[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
All right, we saw a numeric example of how those derivatives get computed.
حسنًا، فقد رأينا مثال رقمي حول كيفية حساب تلك المشتقات.
It's really simple computations.
إنها عمليات حسابية بسيطة للغاية.
Now let's go back and interpret a little bit what the derivative means.
والآن، دعونا نعد إلى تفسير ما يقصد بالمشتقة.
So let's say we have a particular parameter that we're trying to update,
لنفترض أن لدينا معلمة محددة نحاول تحديثها،وهي Wj
w j, and we have a particular data point x i, want to look at its contribution and
ولدينا نقطة بيانات محددة وهي xi، وبالنظر إلى قيمتها
it turns out that for x i, h j(x i) has value one.
يتضح أن في xi فإن (hj(xi تساوي القيمة 1.
Say that that's what happened, so
لنفترض أن هذا ما قد حدث،
what is the contribution that this data point has on the total derivative?
لذا، ما القيمة التي لدى نقطة البيانات هذه على المستوى الكلي للمشتقة؟
So if you call this contribution here delta i, and
فإذا أطلقنا على هذه القيمة المسمى Δi،
I chose hj of xi t1 because then we don't
واخترت أن تكون قيمة (hj(xi هي 1 حتى لا نقلق بعد ذلك
have to worry too much about future value, we can just focus on that difference.
حيال قيمة السمة، ونتمكن من التركيز على الاختلاف فقط.
Let's interpret that difference.
ودعونا نفسر هذا الاختلاف.
So, let's first look at the case where yi is positive,
لذا، دعونا ننظر أولَا إلى الحالة حيث تكون قيمة yi موجبة،
it's a positive training example.
حيث أن هذا مثال تدريب إيجابي.
And, our model, it's pretty sure that
ويؤكد النموذج الذي لدينا أن هذا مثال تدريب إيجابي.
So, it says the probability that y equals +1, it's approximately equal to one.
لذا، يفترض أن الاحتمالية y = +1، تساوي 1 تقريبًا.
So let's interpret what happens.
لنفسر ما يحدث هنا.
So, in this case delta i is going
في هذه الحالة فإن Δi ستكون
to be equal to the difference between one,
مساوية للفرق بين 1،
the indicator function is paused there and the probability here,
حيث أن دالة المؤشر مستبعدة هنا، والاحتمالية هنا
which is approximately one, so this whole thing is going to be approximately zero.
والتي تساوي 1 تقريبًا، وبالتالي فهذه المعادلة ستساوي صفرًا تقريبًا.
In other words, the data points are positive,
وبعبارة أخرى، فإن نقطة البيانات موجبة،
the model thinks it's a positive data point.
ويعمل النموذج من منطلق أن هذه نقطة بيانات موجبة.
So that the contribution here is zero means don't change anything.
لذا، فكون القيمة هنا هي صفر، فإن هذا يعني لا تغير أي شيء.
From the perspective of this parameter, you shouldn't change anything.
ووفقًا لمنظور هذه المعلمة، لا يجب تغيير أي شيء.
Which makes sense.
مما يجعل الأمر منطقيًا.
You get it right.
لقد فهمت الأمر بشكل صحيح.
Let's see what happens if you get it completely wrong.
دعونا نرى ما قد يحدث إذا فهمت الأمر بشكل خاطئ تمامًا.
So this is the second case where it's a positive training example but
وهذه هي الحالة الثانية، حيث يوجد مثال تدريب إيجابي ولكن
the probability y = +1 is approximately 0.
الاحتمالية y = +1 تساوي القيمة 0 تقريبًا.
We are getting this training example totally wrong.
ونحن نفهم مثال التدريب هذا بشكل خاطئ تمامًا.
In this case delta i is the difference between
في هذه الحالة فإن Δi هي الفرق بين
the indicator, which has a value 1 and
المؤشر والذي هو القيمة 1
the probability here has a value 0 and so it's approximately 1.
والاحتمالية هنا تساوي القيمة 0، لذا فإن المعادلة هنا تساوي 1 تقريبًا.
So delta i is really big.
لذا، فإن Δi كبيرة حقًا.
And so what is this imply?
وماذا يعني هذا؟
This implies that this data point wants us to increase
هذا يعني أن نقطة البيانات تلك تتطلب أن نقوم بزيادة
the coefficient, w j, the one that we just tried to increase.
المعامل Wj، وهو المعامل الذي حاولنا زيادته.
It says push the derivative up, add this little delta that makes it more positive.
ويشير ذلك إلى دفع المشتقة لأعلى، وإضافة القيمة دلتا التي تجعل من المعادلة إيجابية.
And remember that if xhj is a positive number and is
وتذكر أن إذا كانت قيمة (hj(x تساوي رقمًا موجبًا
getting multiplied by a bigger coefficient because we just made it a little bigger,
وتم ضربها في معامل أكبر، لأننا جعلنا قيمتها أكبر قليلًا،
that implies that the score of hi
فهذا يعني أن مجموع hi
becomes larger and that implies in a sense the probability
يصبح أكبر، مما يعني أن الاحتمالية
that y is equal to +1 given xi and w increases.
(y=+1|xi,w) قيمتها تزيد أيضًا.
And that is extremely intuitive.
وهذا أمر بديهي للغاية.
So, if we're getting the data point really wrong, we get this positive delta i,
لذا، إذا فهمنا نقطة البيانات بشكل خاطئ، فسنحصل على Δi الموجبة هذه
which is going to increase my parameter, which is is going to increase my score,
مما يؤدي إلى زيادة المعلمة، مما يؤدي إلى زيادة المجموع
which makes in the next step.
مما يؤدي في الخطوة التالية
In the next iteration, the probability this data point's positive higher.
إلى جعل الاحتمالية الموجبة لنقطة البيانات هذه ذات قيمة أعلى.
So we're going the right direction.
لذا، سنذهب في الاتجاه الصحيح.
Now, let's go through this a little quicker, we can look at the case where
والآن، دعونا نخوض في هذا الأمر بشكل أسرع قليلًا، حيث يمكننا النظر في حالة حيث
yi is negative and you just get the same thing with flipped sign.
تكون قيمة yi سالبة، وسنحصل على نفس القيمة ولكن بعلامة معكوسة.
So, for example, If yi is negative but
إذن، على سبيل المثال، إذا كانت قيمة yi سالبة
I'm getting the prediction right, so this is a negative data point.
ولكني أفهم عملية التنبؤ بشكل صحيح، حيث أن هذه نقطة بيانات سالبة.
We'll see that delta i is approximately equal
فسنرى أن Δi تساوي تقريبًا
to 0 which implies don't change anything.
القيمة 0، مما يعني ألا تغير أي شيء.
It makes sense, I've got everything right, why would I change anything?
فهذا منطقي، لقد حصلت على كل شيء بشكل صحيح، فلما قد أغير أي شيء؟
However, in the case where the data points were negative, but
ومع ذلك، في حالة كون نقطة البيانات سالبة، ولكن
the prediction I've made was that there were positive data point, then delta i
عملية التنبؤ التي قمت بها كانت بناءً على نقطة بيانات إيجابية، فإن Δi
would be the difference between the indicator which in this case is 0,
ستكون الفرق بين المؤشر والذي في تلك الحالة يساوي 0،
and the probability, which is approximately 1.
والاحتمالية والتي تساوي 1 تقريبًا.
So this delta i would be negative, would be approximately -1.
لذا فإن Δi هذه ستكون سالبة، وتساوي تقريبًا القيمة -1.
Which would lead wj to decrease
مما يؤدي إلى تناقص قيمة Wj
which would imply that
مما يعني أن مجموع
the score of xi decreases and
القيمة xi سيتناقص
it leads to the probability
وسيؤدي إلى تناقص قيمة الاحتمالية
of y=+1 given x i and
(y=+1|xi,w)
w, to decrease.
.
Yay.
رائع.
It fits the negative datapoint and we get it wrong, we decrease the coefficient
إذا كانت نقطة بيانات سالبة وتم فهمها بشكل خاطئ، فإننا سنقلل قيمة المعامل
to make that probability of it being positive smaller and
لجعل احتمالية كونه موجبًا أقل
increase the probability it will be negative.
وزيادة احتمالية كونه سالبًا.
So cool.
رائع.
We've gone through a little bit of interpretation of how this gradient
فقد خضنا خلال القليل من التفسير حول كيف يمكن لمعامل التدرج هذا
helps us push the coefficients bigger for positive training example.
أن يساعدنا في دفع المعاملات بقيم أكبر بالنسبة لأمثلة التدريب الموجبة.
And more negative, smaller for negative training examples,
ودفعها بقيم أٌصغر في حالات أمثلة التدريب السالبة،
which is exactly what we wanted for that score function.
وهو بالضبط ما كنا نريده بالنسبة لدالة المجموع تلك.